<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-25T08:50:49-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Lauren Cappiello</title><author><name>Dr. Lauren Cappiello</name><email>cappiello@csus.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Meet The Rescues</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Meet-the-Rescues/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meet The Rescues" /><published>2021-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Meet-the-Rescues</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Meet-the-Rescues/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="meet-the-rescue-animals">Meet the Rescue Animals</h1>

<h2 id="daisy">Daisy</h2>

<p><img src="http://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG-7073.jpg" alt="Daisy lounging" height="400" /> <img src="http://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG-7097.jpg" alt="Daisy and Fiddler snuggling" height="400" /></p>

<p>My husband and I adopted Daisy in 2011. I was volunteering at a low cost spay and neuter clinic helping out with surgical recovery. Someone found her and brought her in with her four kittens. Daisy is 10 or 11 now and spends most of her days sleeping at the top of the cat tree.</p>

<h2 id="fiddler">Fiddler</h2>

<p><img src="http://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG-7815.jpg" alt="Fiddler, upside down" height="400" /> <img src="http://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG-7910.jpg" alt="Fiddler admiring the turtles" height="400" /></p>

<p>A couple of friends started feeding a stray cat that wandered into their yard in earlt 2017. A couple months later she had four kittens in their upstairs closet. We took this perfect floofy angel off their hands. Fiddler is exactly as delightfully fluffy as he looks and has the tiniest “meep” of a meow.</p>

<h2 id="suki">Suki</h2>

<p><img src="http://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG-7187.jpg" alt="Suki" height="400" /> <img src="http://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG-8387.jpg" alt="Suki in a sweater" height="400" /></p>

<p>We rescued Suki after moving to Sacramento in summer 2020. I found her on Craigslist. The guy who got rid of her had a newborn and was keeping her outside all the time because he didn’t know how to manage such a high energy dog. She’s an Austrailian cattle dog mix - a smart, eager-to-please, high-energy breed! She loves to learn and we do a lot of little tricks with her. We named her after a character in Avatar the Last Airbender. She’s my best friend.</p>

<h2 id="sokka">Sokka</h2>

<p><img src="http://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG-9041.jpg" alt="Sokka in the sunshine" height="400" /> <img src="http://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG-9057.jpg" alt="Sokka being a goober" height="400" /> <img src="https://lgpcappiello.github.io/images/IMG_9511.JPG" alt="Sokka napping on my pillow after shoving all of the blankets aside" height="400" /></p>

<p>We got Sokka from Sacramento Independent Animal Rescuers in January 2021. He loves to snuggle. He came to us very shy, but we spent some time working with a trainer to get his confidence up. He’s doing great! Sokka is also named after Avatar the Last Airbender, but we didn’t name him! The rescue named him and he came to us (and to Suki!) with his name. My sister found him for us on Petfinder and it felt like fate :)</p>

<h2 id="the-turtles">The Turtles</h2>

<p>Two red-eared sliders came home with me (as tiny babies) from Chinatown in Los Angeles circa 2014. The friend I’d gone to LA with passed away unexpectedly in 2017 and they’re a sweet reminder of her.</p>]]></content><author><name>Dr. Lauren Cappiello</name><email>cappiello@csus.edu</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meet the Rescue Animals]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">R Shiny: A Dungeons and Dragons Character Generator</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/shinyapp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="R Shiny: A Dungeons and Dragons Character Generator" /><published>2020-07-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-07-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/shinyapp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/shinyapp/"><![CDATA[<p>Shiny is an R package designed to build apps in R. These can be used to build dashboards, create interactive graphics, you name it! Around the time I discovered Shiny, a friend suggested that it would be fun to have an app that automatically generated Dungeons and Dragons characters. Making a fun project out of it is my favorite way to learn something new, so I spent a few hours tackling the basic Shiny app. Thus, the <a href="https://lgpcappiello.shinyapps.io/charactergenerator/">Character Generator</a> was born! It’s not pretty (although that is perhaps a future project), but it was fun to build. These days, when I have a few minutes to play around with Shiny I’m working on adding a mad libs type character backstory generator. These projects may not have a lot of useful real-world applications, but it’s helped me build a skillset with Shiny. Interested in how it works? You can download the R files for the Character Generator <a href="https://github.com/lgpcappiello/shinyapps/tree/master/CharacterGenerator">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Dr. Lauren Cappiello</name><email>cappiello@csus.edu</email></author><category term="r programming" /><category term="just for fun" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Shiny is an R package designed to build apps in R. These can be used to build dashboards, create interactive graphics, you name it! Around the time I discovered Shiny, a friend suggested that it would be fun to have an app that automatically generated Dungeons and Dragons characters. Making a fun project out of it is my favorite way to learn something new, so I spent a few hours tackling the basic Shiny app. Thus, the Character Generator was born! It’s not pretty (although that is perhaps a future project), but it was fun to build. These days, when I have a few minutes to play around with Shiny I’m working on adding a mad libs type character backstory generator. These projects may not have a lot of useful real-world applications, but it’s helped me build a skillset with Shiny. Interested in how it works? You can download the R files for the Character Generator here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning to Love Statistics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/lovestatistics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning to Love Statistics" /><published>2018-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/lovestatistics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/lovestatistics/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post was originally written for UCR GradQuant and the UCR Graduate Student Resource Center blog. It has been lightly edited for relevance.</em></p>

<p>However you feel about statistics – if you love it, are confused by it, or even if you consider it best used as a way to strike fear in the hearts of thine enemies – a basic understanding of the subject is quickly becoming not only a highly desirable skill, but a necessary approach to disseminating information. Most of us already know how to be critical, but developing some level of enthusiasm for data helps nurture the desire to keep asking for more of it. And more data = more information. This is a healthy sense of skepticism, one that sends us down a path of exploration rather than a path of dismissal.</p>

<p>With this in mind, consider that you don’t have to love doing math to appreciate what it does for you. You don’t need advanced calculus (or any calculus, for that matter) to be a critical consumer of data. At the heart of every piece of technology, feat of engineering, investment, and even baked good you use is a scientific approach supported by mathematics. 
Consider, if you will, baking a loaf of bread. Proteins in flour form an elastic network that allows the loaf to rise and stay risen; leavening agents such as yeast and baking create carbon dioxide as a byproduct to make the bread rise; an egg might help bring a hydrophobic fat into your mixture… the possibilities are endless.</p>

<p align="center"><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/26gJAuwR7TAz5NRy8/giphy.gif" height="200" /></p>
<p align="center"><small>Yes, that is a lion made entirely out of bread.</small></p>

<p>That said, not every possibility makes a pleasant loaf of bread. Optimization, whether approached statistically or by many generations of trial and error, is the mathematical underpinning of that delicious bread lion. (Click <a href="http://www.berries.com/blog/science-of-baking">here</a> for a fun infographic on the science of baking.)
Now that you’re primed with a world class bread lion, I’m just going to go ahead and say it: math is cool. People have a natural desire to describe and explain the world around them. Mathematics and statistics let us do exactly that. Perhaps fields like physics and chemistry come to mind but, in fact, fields as diverse as art history and linguistics have started to incorporate statistical approaches. Music is incredibly mathematical (which is not to say that it’s necessarily formulaic!). Philosophy, mathematics, and computer science students all take logic courses. In short, math worms its way into all aspects of our lives.</p>

<p align="center"><img src="http://giphygifs.s3.amazonaws.com/media/i8LQDpYfnzYWc/giphy.gif" alt="Fractals" width="200" /></p>
<p align="center"><small>Fractals are a mathematical concept wherein an object displays infinite self-similarity. Fun!</small></p>

<p>Statistics takes all of that information and brings in another dimension: the quantification of uncertainty. Whenever we gather data, there is some degree of uncertainty about how well our data represents the population that we are interested in. This is the primary role of statistics: to determine exactly how much uncertainty there is and quantify that in a meaningful way. If you randomly find 100 people and ask them all how many cats they have and I randomly find two people and ask them the same question, chances are that your data is a lot more meaningful than mine. Maybe you got a mean of two cats and I got a mean of eight.</p>

<p align="center"><img src="http://giphygifs.s3.amazonaws.com/media/40Fpxgn6Yq640/giphy.gif" alt="Kittens" /></p>
<p align="center"><small>Eight cats may not be reasonable, but that’s the dream.</small></p>

<p>Without statistics, we have no way to quantitatively demonstrate that your estimate is better than mine. With statistics, we can develop a confidence interval, test your mean of two against my claim of eight, and more! As a critical consumer of information, keeping this in mind whenever someone presents a numeric factoid is a great place to start on your journey to statistical skepticism.</p>

<p>Keeping up with current events is enormously important and factoids about bread are interesting, but at this point you may be wondering what all of this means to your work as a graduate student. As students and scholars, statistics are a part of just about every discipline. Even if your own work does not require any statistical analyses, a basic understanding of quantitative methods will allow you to keep up-to-date with the literature in your field. Developing a basic understanding of the mathematical underpinnings behind the statistical analyses you come across will help you to be a more critical reader and a better researcher. If you do need statistics for your work, taking the time to truly appreciate what statistics can do for you is the first step toward describing your time spent running analyses as “interesting” rather than “tedious”.</p>

<p align="center"><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/26xBI73gWquCBBCDe/giphy.gif" alt="Confused Winona Ryder" height="200" /></p>

<p>At this point, you may be asking yourself if these concepts are really all that accessible. Everyone who can think logically can learn math! If you are uncomfortable with math, it may take a little bit of additional work, but you can do it!</p>]]></content><author><name>Dr. Lauren Cappiello</name><email>cappiello@csus.edu</email></author><category term="education" /><category term="statistics" /><category term="just for fun" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post was originally written for UCR GradQuant and the UCR Graduate Student Resource Center blog. It has been lightly edited for relevance.]]></summary></entry></feed>